software engineering radio episode 94
open-source business models with the
relay
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se radio
prints irrelevant and detailed
discussions and interviews on soft
engineering topics every ten days thanks
to our audience and the partners listed
on our web site for supporting the
porkchop
[Music]
welcome everybody here is another
episode of SU radio your favorite soft
engineering podcast this episode is a
little bit less technical than something
than some of the else we've had this
episode is on how you can make money
with open source more or less don't
forget that this is the third episode in
which we have the little advertising at
the end from Jose they're still looking
well I presume they're still looking for
new colleagues so if you speak German
you should listen to it otherwise skip
it but please let us know what you think
about this kind of advertisement okay so
let's get on with the show here is the
episode I recorded in Santa Clara
when I was at Eclipse con with Doug have
fun so we're talking to Doug really
today some of you german-speaking
listeners probably know him from the
Gogh book which he translated so welcome
Doug thank you thanks for having me
Marcus sure better so what are you up to
today I live in the Silicon Valley I
work for s AP labs and in particular IP
research where I lead the open-source
research group so I mostly deal with
open source professionally these days
not so much doing open source but
research into it how could I say P
benefit how do companies benefit from
open source so by that time you probably
guessed what this show is going to be
about it's also listed in the title so
you probably know anyway it's about open
source professional open source the
business models and the philosophies
behind it and there's obviously a good
person to speak to so get us started in
theory open source is about making the
world better right you have this idea of
of doing something for free and giving
it away for free and everybody can see
what you do so there is this whole
philosophy of improving the state of the
universe mmm-hmm how does this go
together with this professional slash
business open source kind of thing so I
think in theory and in practice open
source is for some about improving the
world that is certainly true and that's
not to be neglected but
as you say it's about commercial
interest these days so you have we have
both we have volunteers we have the
people who just like to code and we have
clear commercial interests on open
source and the various business models
on how you can make money of open source
there probably as many business models
as there are companies yeah so is it
exclusive or is it either commercial
let's say as an example SpringSource
more completely voluntary or is there
also a way of mixing it what's the role
of the voluntaries in a professional
environment maybe ya know volunteers are
always individual people so it's like
someone who likes to program and who
would like to wants to contribute they
just do that the commercial players are
of course companies so it's a legal
entity that has a commercial interest
and so we see how commercial companies
sponsor create or contribute to open
source projects for different purposes
for example because they believe open
source gets them faster adoption of
their product yeah okay so just to set
the stage in this episode we're going to
talk about professional open source
about the business models so we don't
talk about the let's say philosophy of
this other thing mainly so let's first
start with looking at certain existing
open source business models I guess the
the obvious one for me at least because
I'm involved in one I'm most earnest
open architectural stuff and my business
is consulting for this thing so that's
probably one way to do it yes that's
certainly one the way we look at it from
a research perspective is that we
recognize open source is a tool to get
you somewhere with your business model
and your business and how to create a
revenue stream and this tool has three
main effects that you utilize in your
business model so for example the most
well-known is the is open sourcing in
order to get speedier adoption and the
market and based on that for example P
companies have built the dual license
strategy
most notably my sequel but other
companies as well so what does it do a
license strategy the dual license
strategy is a strategy were the legal
entity the company owns the code it's
not the volunteers who contribute okay
cause now the volunteers it's a company
pay it's people paid by the company and
hence the company owns the copyright and
thus the company goes to market was the
open source was the product the database
in the case of my Sakura and all they
effectively do is they provide the
source code and people pick up on it and
possibly improve it but that never makes
it back into the product unless unless
the contributor gives back to my sequel
the rights to the code who gives up
their copyright so my secret tightly
controls the copyright it's their
product and what they do then is they
give it away for free under a GPL
license and they sell services or sell
rights to use it based on a different
license a proprietary license their own
license to commercial customers for
example want to build applications based
on my SQL my sequel so in that case the
I mean open source is often associated
with this flossing free open free open
source software right so in this case
the most important aspect is probably
the free part because it's not like you
can easily contribute so the reason why
there are two licenses is it is free to
use under the GPL license and maybe we
need to explain how that works
detection or licenses later also okay so
basically what the GPL lets you do is
you can use it but if you want to use it
commercially if you don't have just a
private use if you have a commercial use
you would have to provide your source
code to whoever is interested and that's
of course not what commercial company
using my sequel I would like to do so
basically using the GPL license the
product makes it into companies gets
used for free but if something is more
something more is built around then the
company the usage using company
typically turns around and once a
commercial license was proper support
off the product
okay so there's professional license
then relieves you from the requirement
to also open source your own product and
it gives you probably come well a
support contract with all the bells and
whistles that you would expect yes it
has different users father for the
buying company but knows if it's just
the user it's obviously the support and
services the subscription water the
place to call the guaranteed so 24-hour
support if something goes wrong so so
this professional is a pop thing can
this is this only legally possible so
let's say I'm the company and I develop
the system I make it available on the
GPL people can use it and I also do this
other license with a professional
support now assume it's different assume
the system is really developed by this
open source community with people from
different companies and volunteers right
and the product is really open source
you can use it professionally without
you know this licensing thing it's
probably that not GPL can a company
still come in and say we provide
professional support and support
contracts and stuff for such a license
thing yes absolutely
let me first clarify two terms which I
think are important right are we
distinguish between community open
source and commercial open source and
community open source is a project or a
source code that is shared by a
community where there is no single legal
entity that controls their commercial
open source then is the situation I'd my
sequel server CRM a single company
control so they can give out different
licenses now services around community
open source projects are definitely
Pasir everyone is allowed basically to
enter this market because nobody stops
them yeah the issue though is that
because the come the project or the
product the source code is really shared
and there are no barriers to entry the
kind of revenue you can generate from
that market is is hard to get so let's
assume there is
a lot of demand then there will be lots
of companies there's little demand then
lots of companies they leave the market
so basically you're pricing from a
service perspective as pricing is pretty
much mark-up over cost so it's not
sudden high price you said because
you're the 800-pound gorilla but rather
it's in strong competition with others
yeah sure but what you could do for
example is let you know 24 hours support
of something if the bug is found
I guarantee because my company happens
to host two or three committers that
that we fix it and give you a new build
within you know so there could be this
additional value this is definitely a
business model and we do see that there
was a recent IDC study though that
suggested that these types of services
which are focused on a single open
source project that these types of
services are actually not that much
sought-after right and so it was quite
amazing for me too because I believe
this business model worked reasonably
well I didn't think it was a great
business to be in but I thought it would
work but this IDC study found that
individual components and the video
projects did not have much attendant
services this is to be distinguished
from like Red Hat and all that which
basically are about the configuration or
a larger stack just services a view
server focused on exactly one you're a
small example exactly that is a hard
business and apparently customers are
not buying as much as one would expect
okay so let's look at the next possible
way of doing it so what came to my mind
is the Gentle where thing where there is
this open source will all go uml and
they basically took over the codebase
and edit additional features made more
usable made it more whatever reliable
something and then sold that as a
commercial product yeah that is
definitely something we're seeing in the
market too basically taking a community
project which has to be it has to be a
community open source project typically
and then from providing proprietary
add-ons that is possible if the license
permits these add-ons in such a way that
you don't have to open-source them
because if you would have to open-source
them too you would not be able to build
a
positional advantage around your
additions now gentle where is one
example the big one that I'm using is
enterprise TV and PostgreSQL so Postgres
gel is another database competing with
MySQL these are the two open-source
databases and the exactly complementary
models meaning PostgreSQL has a very
very permissive license and enterprise
DB employs several of the committers
which contribute to the core project so
the overall user community is benefiting
but then enterprise DB as you
illustrated in the chanter very example
two builds additional hats on gives
Postgres additional enterprise strength
SP and that is a good business to be in
because you can really build your own
advantage and it's pretty close to
traditional proprietary close source
models because it's close sauce that
makes your that makes your competitive
advantage
another example comes to my mind is the
Eclipse Foundation where a bunch of
companies go together get together make
certain let's say based technologies
open source and as I heard this week on
the conference on Eclipse Khan that's
why I'm here
make sure that the code on eclipse is
actually not that great and so that the
contributing companies have a way of
building products on top of it and the
nature of it was meant completely in
earnest yeah I would not advise to do
that and the reason is that people are
simply not stupid so I mean to force
them into something like this for only
rice bad blood but Eclipse is a really
interesting example as I said initially
open-source is a tool to give you three
key effects we see one of which was
speedier adoption
that's what MySQL and PostgreSQL are
doing and some others as well the
Eclipse platform and IBM's interest
behind Eclipse are in my opinion a
different effect they are playing off on
and that is to shift revenue between
markets meaning to shift revenue from a
market that is actually not very
attractive or that you cannot really
address
because elementals exactly because
someone is keeping an occupied or it's a
really hard time they've had a really
hard time with with related competing a
glass visual studio to shift it into a
place where you have better as better
positioned to rock off so what IBM does
is the Eclipse platform draws many
companies together it's a real platform
and of course they're selling the
rational tool suite it's true that they
have of course the conflicts you talked
about so for example IBM also is still
selling clearcase and so I always
wondered why the support for CVS is
great and not so much for subversion
yeah they stand at Eclipse Java towards
for example or in general but what IBM
really does is its commoditizing the
basic basic tools platforms and shifting
and thereby enabling themselves
basically to provide better tours on
without having having a reduced cost on
the platform another example of that is
in the modeling's basically it's
modeling where there's a whole bunch of
existing projects on eclipse and then
for example bawlin comes in takes these
things provides a bunch of knives buoys
around it and ships it is together
what is it 2008 or something yeah it I
would like to add that I use because he
pointed to Eclipse I used this as an
example for shifting revenues between
markets if all of these business models
are sometimes taking different bits and
pieces together in itself to make my
point about shifting revenues between
markets a clearer or cleaner example is
for example is IBM support of Linux so
directed mostly against Windows of
course by trying to commoditize or by
trying to keep down the amount of money
that Microsoft can charge for windows
because Linux is becoming a stronger
competitor the money available at a
customer can is the money is split
differently so less goes to the
operating system license revenue ends in
to some other places another way of
looking at that is probably that
if I let's say I Oracle supports Linux
mm-hmm then people can buy well don't
have to spend as much license fees for
whatever Solaris or Windows and then as
you say we'll probably be willing to
spend more on the database yeah exactly
if you only looked at the software part
of the total IT stack or so literally
every company that has a stronghold on
one component would like to be all other
components to be available for free
because then it can charge most for its
own component IBM again is particularly
interesting the cause so an example as
IBM sponsoring Linux Oracle of course
would like the operator operating system
to be free osip definitely would love to
be all databases and all operating
systems to be free etc iBM is a
particularly interesting case because
they can run circles around literally
everyone and that's because they are
strong not just in software but in
services and hardware as well in
particular services so services
companies for example would love to be
to have but more or less all software
for free because all of the revenue all
of the customers money would become
services revenue implementation services
configuration services etc which goes
back to the original business model we
had which is providing professional
services for open source products yeah
that that's true uh-huh
so closing the circle the problem is we
didn't finish yet so we have to open the
circle again because it seems there are
more one thing that I wrote down here is
commercial hosting services for open
source and products like for example if
you have the Tomcat server and I provide
you know a server farm where people can
run their web app on a you know on the
Tomcat that another thing that's
interesting in this space or is this too
far removed from the fact that it's an
open source product it is an interesting
question
we haven't looked much into it because
it would seem like another cutthroat
business because standard open source
software everyone can do it everyone can
open a hosting service I think it's so
what I see is tor living here in the
valley talking with lots of startups
looking at how they try to go
get by on a shoestring is they have
almost all standardized more or less
standard architectures open source text
underlying the welcome lamp and lap and
Postgres possibly isolated EP yeah so
PostgreSQL is actually quite a strong
database yes us by many so these these
stacks look quite similar and so I can
see how a service can be standardized on
that and how this would open up a notch
customer base because they're used to
these types of software but then again
it sounds a bit like markup over cost
pricing usually not if you're coming
from this it's that's the situation you
have in many industries but of course
you would like to be able to charge
prices that are better than them just
starting with your costs right any other
business models we when we prepared
prepared the the questions here it
didn't think of there are other business
models for example you can provide a
fair amount of consulting around open
source there's like here in the valley a
small boutique but fairly well going one
is the alliance group you have some
larger ones like open logic this to me
feels more like a traditional
consultancy so their competence or their
the competitive advantage comes simply
from having good people from knowing how
their consulting processes work from
being good at sales and customer
acquisition yeah and they just choose
open source as the subject but it could
be probably any other subject too so is
it also like for them a way of marketing
to say we are
I mean it's open source such a big topic
today that putting it into your strategy
and saying we provide training or
consulting especially for open source
products is that is that like brand you
know like maybe it's not Microsoft stuff
we do open so I don't know so no it's
just a domain where you can provide
consulting service intellectual services
around that it's definitely a good bet
these days
we just published a paper about the
growth of open source and we found that
the open source code base is growing
exponentially and the number of viable
active open source projects is also
growing exponentially quite important
for us IP to realize that since it means
or it imply it in this case that open
source is growing into more and more
application domains including business
application right and that you need to
hold against that that closed source and
the packaged applications space is
certainly not growing exponentially so
literally open source is eating right
into a closed source and for that the
question is on what base then of course
that's one thing to say it's growing
exponentially but then is it on a
significant level already yeah that's
hard to measure if you look at the pure
revenues of open source applications in
the packaged application market it's at
0.7 percent so it's below 1 percent how
which i think is actually non-trivial
already I mean you get different
reactions but this is really the nominal
value now you need to add that on one
download there is maybe 10 you on ten
downloads there's one paying user and
then what they actually pay is compared
to traditional closed source typically
much cheaper so doing different
calculations we can go up to like 27
percent of the packaged application
marker consisting of open source
software package that sounds much better
that sounds like a good consulting space
to be in there are not many consulting
companies although I would never start a
company doing consulting for open source
right I mean I do consulting for I don't
know web frameworks in the open source
base or model driven frameworks in the
open source base so just saying open
source consulting for me seems to be to
unspecific but I might be wrong I think
you're making a good point because those
companies that we observe that try to
provide more strategic consulting still
do this on a fairly general level which
means maybe the mark
obviously the market is still developing
but I'm pretty sure you're right that
this is where it's going that companies
will differentiate and build expertise
on specific domains I guess also there
is a difference whether you do technical
consulting for certain products or
whether as you said you do strategic
consulting on the role of open source
systems in an enterprise so let's talk a
little bit about the chances and risks
of working in this space or doing
something here so what do companies gain
by open sourcing assets they have and
maybe which assets should you open
source
mm-hmm well let me start by a negative
example you should not open source
something where you just want to get rid
of it because that's not how it works I
get approached frequently how do I open
source and I ask why do you want to open
source and well we got our resources cut
and we don't want to let it die but
really don't really don't have any time
to spend on it so that's the idea of let
the rest of the world maintain it yeah
give it to the community and expecting
the community will just pick it up and
write for and of course that's not how
it works if you open source you need to
invest additional resources to help grow
and build that community in the first
place so when you open source what you
should do you should really have a
strategic goal associated with with that
such an element sourcing so such as
again these three examples that I
mentioned you want to shift revenues
became is you want to you want to speed
up adoption by giving it away for free
in quotation marks and the third one I
didn't talk about yet by creating a
superior product by working intensely
with a community that are it's basically
basically user innovation and it's a
form all it's an advanced form
interesting from a research perspective
and advanced form of product management
in my opinion okay so mmm-hmm there's
maybe one other one that comes to my
mind in this very specific niche and
that is if you do security software
mm-hmm just let everybody look into it
and see there is no backdoor you know
this kind of stuff
that can't be an argument in that in
that space okay so again you should if
you if you if you open source something
then don't do it just to get rid of the
work do it because you have those goals
and you have to invest at least
initially to to get everything started
so I guess building a community is
probably the key to it mm-hmm well so to
build a community what you do is you
create a website and let it go course
not
so any ideas about what it takes to
build a community that's probably a
separate topic you know oh yeah but but
just a couple of pointers this is a long
and very interesting topic because that
is something everyone has to get right
if they want to create a successful open
source project I can tell you from our
own experiences at si P we have an
internal software Forge where we which
is not visible to the outside but which
is open to everyone so we do see these
open source effects and it's a sequence
of steps that basically need to be
supported or enabled by software and by
the behavior of people and that is first
of all the project literally needs to be
findable so if you don't if it's on some
random server at some random URL you
won't find it so be on SourceForge or be
at a visible place put your stuff on
fresh meat or ollo and just make sure
that it can be found now you need those
initial peoples who make it useful to
users of course but what they want to do
in building their community is draw
volunteers so in order to draw
volunteers you need to be open and
transparent in your work people need to
be able to read up on what's going on
yeah and you need to make the entrance
order for an initial contribution as
small as possible as simple as hitting
the reply button in a forum so I guess
also the the code needs to be documented
needs to be in a you know accessible
understandable exactly but I think most
people evolved from being users to
becoming developers to becoming the
committers so I don't think people jump
right into the core I'm sure there are
some who jump right into the code but
most start out as a user do some testing
and or answer questions or ask
in the forums here incrementally draw
them in so so again let's assume I
open-source something for one of those
strategic reasons we talked about before
of course there is the risk that my
competitors pick up this thing and
improve their own maybe commercial
products and so I you know I give mine
away and the other is improve theirs and
make more money is that a problem it is
if you're not smart about it but it's
actually fairly easy to handle and
that's because we need to go back to
this distinction between communities
open source and commercial open source
community open source the rights the
copyright is spread around a community
and there's typically less than only one
license that regulates things and
commercial open source a single legal
entity owns it and so if you provide a
product to the outside world under a
community license then what you just
under an S community open source and
under a permissive license so it always
goes together then yes you can be ripped
off but now you need to look at your
strategic goal community open source and
permissive license you use that
typically when you want to shift
revenues between markets so you want to
not necessarily kill the initial market
but just reduce the impact now for
commercial open source you use a dual
license strategy or something similar so
you are actually maintaining the full
rights to the software and are
positioning yourself as squarely in the
center of the community so you are the
obvious go to a person the software
bears your name you on the website which
which is naturally pointed to by that
name and so while some competitor can
use GPL based code they are just being a
much much weaker position than you to
provide services okay but I mean they
can still take a look at the code and
and and just learn how to do things and
then build a commercial product that
picks up those patterns that's not
really possible yeah but you need to see
the company that wants to earn its
livelihood by by open sourcing a
commercial open source product
it doesn't stand still it's it's a I'm
not sure it's a winner-takes-all game
but it very much looks like that you
need to build that community you need to
get that speedy adoption going you need
to get those smart people in the
community to tell you what other right
features and thus be implementing the
right features best for your customers
and then so that someone else try to
steal from you but what's their
competitive advantage over you there'll
always be a step behind No and probably
their third tool might be more expensive
since it is not open source maybe to
make a commercial product so why should
ups buy it
so yeah exactly maybe it's commercial
but even if they are cheaper because
they really are in a cheap loan country
so it's the most it's not likely to be
the best product or best project because
the originator has the speed has the
moment run okay so before we talk about
the licenses sometimes when I hear about
these kinds of business models around it
there is it sounds like there's an exit
strategy which basically says I mean
obviously red hen with J monastery boss
and also I mean I think it's a question
of time until one of the big guys buy a
spring source right I mean it's obvious
where they're going yeah so is this a
valid idea um exit strategy B to be
bought up yeah exit strategy is a term
for startup right anymore what happens
and I think open source is just a
business model it's not clear to me that
it implies I haven't really thought
about it in much detail it's not clear
to me that it implies a specific exit
strategy I think it's open to any
startup whether it uses an open source
approach go to market approach or not to
go the usual ways meaning get bought the
typical thing well like typical thing is
go broke but get bored or possibly IPO
and make it on their own
so I think these are all options I can
imagine that you clearly are public open
source company red hat and some success
with the
next big topic licenses all right so why
don't we start by or by you giving us a
brief overview of the well of the most
well known most important open-source
licenses and maybe you know why they are
different than how they are different
and things okay I absolutely have to say
the to be expected thing I am NOT a
lawyer all right none of this is legal
advice but quite honestly even for
someone who deals with open source on a
daily basis it's easily confusing right
so but let me give it a try and maybe
you bring in a lawyer we are licensed
experts near the point of time the key
differentiator is of course between a
permissive license and a viral license
or as a broker license a permissive
license like the BSD licenses or apache
license they allow and we want to take
the code modify it and distribute it
without having to open source the
modifications that's the key part so
while you take something in you are not
constrained to private use even if you
have a commercial use you do not need to
provide code back to a community and
quite frankly why that may sound like
stealing to some it really isn't that
that simply because if you make
modifications for yourself then you are
creating your own maintenance burden
right so most companies will think twice
whether permissive or not whether to
contribute back or not now the rest of
proko license most notably the GPL but I
also would like to mention the affero
GPL so because it was in the press
recently I come to that maybe in a
second the GPL required that requires
that for non for non private users like
commercial users basically anything that
implies distribution of code that you
have to open source the gyro
modifications to the code
to anyone who comes asking and that of
course is the reciprocal reciprocal or
sometimes called viral nature of the GPL
viral because it infects the other
software all examine sources once you
contribute whatever you do its sucked in
and it spreads to your contribution and
I'm not sure why or less the right term
right the point is really just they
wanted to make sure that you're
benefiting then you should be giving
back and the interesting thing of course
is that the the doula that do a license
strategy is built around the GPL and the
GPL is was like something like 70% of
the most dominant license but for two
very different reasons for the for the
philosophical reasons of sharing and
giving back on the one hand and for the
for the very capitalistic reason of
stalling your competitor from ripping
off your codebase and the dual license
mataji so it's both very socialist and
very capitalist at the same time isn't
that a nice dichotomy there is also the
LGPL license which stands for I think
less of GPL is that doesn't mean it's
less strict about having to open-source
your own thing yes
so the original intent of the LGPL and
back granted was still called the
library GPL was to let you use el GPL
code in your system without having to
provide the source code of your system
if you don't actually change that source
code so that's why it's a library it's
you include you link the library this
all gets very quickly very tricky it all
depends on the definition of what is
derived code how does code link with
each other I mean it's very obvious if
you modify an original fire that you've
modified an or eternal fire but what
about static linking what about dynamic
linking what about web services calls
what kind of connection between two
pieces of code as that establish
and when does you code five fall under
the license of that use code and we're
not another example in that space could
be if I use a GPL open-source piece of
code during construction of my own
system code generator or an ID yeah
does that make my own code I mean I'm
not including it in the product it's not
there at runtime but I included in the
included in the production of my system
yeah it's probably more to the side of
not using right so it's probably
relatively safe I think it's safe just
imagine the GCC so you compile your code
that's fine but it gets tricky or if he
pretty quickly what about the code
generated code depends on some libraries
and only runs for Solaris and then those
are under here perhaps GPL so it's it's
sometimes very tricky for commercial
software vendors mmm-hmm since we talked
about Eclipse before
is there anything notable about the
eclipse public license EPL it's a by and
large permissive license I am actually
not that much involved with Eclipse
while I work for RSA P&S ap is involved
with eclipse we are both contributing
and actually leading eclipse components
these days we're very proud of that
achievement what comes to my mind that
needs to be thought about by anyone
venturing in the space is of course the
issue of patterns is the issue of how
they're you know you do you regulate
that you can always put a pattern you
can implement source code that infringes
on someone's patterns more professional
I kind of consider them kind of second
generation licenses like the Eclipse
license tries to deal with it tries to
regulate it through the contributor
agreement yes so the Apache Software
Foundation the Eclipse Foundation they
all require that anyone who contributes
code sign an agreement I honestly don't
actually know how whether this really
completes completely deals with those
patterns or not I actually think it
doesn't so I don't know either but what
they also what I heard
they have is this very fancy piece of
software which goes through code that's
contributed and tries to find patent
infringement or something or copyright
infringement so I don't know if this is
a rumor or whether these kinds of
systems really exist but I know that
they are very strict about about the IP
process if they call it I can imagine I
don't know about how they could find out
about patent violations I can imagine
that they use something like Black Ducks
software which checks our code for
whether it has been copied and pasted
from other code so SIA
for example so that know by way of copy
and paste GPL code suddenly gets
submitted so it knows all the GPL code
that software yeah IP central I think
it's the product they literally they
download all the open-source projects
they classify them by license they I
think they call it genetic finite
fingerprinting of mode and then
companies can use that or Eclipse
Foundation could use it I don't know
whether they're using it to match up
code contributions whether they have a
possibly being derived from source
projects that may not be compatible my
license I guess building such a product
would be another open source business
model I thought about it earlier but
their software is clearly proprietary as
a comment and money with the riser point
yeah it's you're right open source opens
up many opportunity can I mention the
affero GPL of course so what about it
yeah okay so yeah it's it's not as
well-known and maybe as it should be
because it's a really interesting
development the GPL version 2 which is
probably still the dominant license was
conceived at a point of time where
software as a service was not a big
thing right like 91 I believe so it was
always a big issue does providing a web
service through the net does that
commercial web service does that
constitute distribution of code should
require building such a service that you
open-source your code if you build on
the alt code so if my web server is use
the GPL code yeah Michael Amtrak okay so
if you build on the lamp stack or you
modify or you use MySQL maybe you've
modify it but you really just use it you
don't cook you don't provide copies off
you might ask you what you just run it
on your server then the GPL version 2 in
my understanding would not require you
to open-source you may ask you our
modifications right and then came along
the GPR version 3 and everyone hoped it
would fix that so called ASP loophole
right hey maybe more SaaS or SAS
loophole these days fulfillment exactly
and it didn't and it's unclear why in my
opinion I'm not enough involved in that
so basically people found a workaround
and that is the affero GPL also in
version 3 which as you said is pretty
unknown but that license requires that
if you make modifications to MySQL and
run a web service of it then if MySQL
was under airfare or GPR which was
probably never will be but if it was
then you would have to provide your
modifications and what's noteworthy is
the affero GPL has recently become OSI
approved license so it's one of the I'm
not sure where they are right now maybe
a hundred current open source initiative
approved licenses like the GPL there are
a hundred opens offline oh this is
embarrassing I really should know
whether it's fifty or hundred ok look at
like five open source dot or no no no no
there's any number of variations ok and
there are many nice and C's that try to
be as open source as they can without
actually giving you the full rights of
open source meaning you have the right
or get the source code modify and
redistribute your modification so I
guess one recommendation to companies or
individuals who want to open source
something is probably then not to invent
their own license but rather to take an
existing one because it's kind of
legally proven right yeah so
it certainly advisable not to do your
own thing and you can pick one from
those approved by the OSI it's not
exactly legal the OSI is a nonprofit
organization founded by our agreement
Andrews parents I believe and so it's
kind of an by the fact or nonprofit that
approves licenses no I don't think
there's a notion of legal license or
illegal license not what I meant I meant
it's if I come up with a license I have
to make sure that the actual legal
wording in it actually enforces what I
wanted to info right so existing
licenses are proven in the sense that
everybody knows what they mean if they
have maybe been Eve in court cases about
it it's like reinventing your own
encryption algorithm same stupid idea
yeah that's of course true I mean if
you're sitting at home you're a
one-person open-source project before
you get into legalese it's definitely
better to adopt the Ison's that has been
vetted by lawyers right yeah so since we
were talking about this professional
open-source thing and the business
relationship are there any of those
licenses that are better for this well
for making money with open-source
software or does it really depend on
what you want to do it clearly depends
on what you want to do it's a sequence
of steps which is like what is the main
effect you want to cause in the market
and how does that define your revenue
stream then if open source is the tool
that lets you do that like after avenues
between markets then you need to look at
what's the right license in that
specific context so again for shifting
revenue between markets it's typically a
permissive license you actually want to
Mallis we'd use the revenue in a
specific market so you want as many
people to come in as possible so you
don't make it easy make it you lower the
barriers to entering services around
such a component as much as you can and
father's its other so the GPL again for
the dual license strategy that's the big
sledgehammer to keep your competitors in
check and stop them from ripping off
your work
so let's look at a couple of specific
interesting points here so the first one
we shot it down here was that if you
look at professional open source then
most of that stuff is with really big
companies like Oracle or IBM obviously
with eclipse
so it's this professional open source
thing only for the big big guys or is it
do you know of examples that where
smaller companies are involved
well MySQL could be an example maybe
yeah so I think the term professional
open source that you're using maybe it
derives from kind of more professional
services around an ad so that typically
suggests you have a working consulting
services operation there would suggest
you're talking about larger companies
when MySQL of course provides services
surrounded sets product yeah I'd call
them commercially because I think that's
the term that sugarcrm came up with yeah
I guess professional commercial means
the same here yeah so I think it's open
to everyone but I would be repeating
myself so if you're if you're really
providing professional services around
just one component it's a tough market
if you are a large company and you're
providing services around many
components that's a different thing
because you're integrating them already
so we're head is not providing services
around just one specific resource but
they're added value is really in the
certified stack and services around that
but it's tricky so for example spike
sauce tries to provide configurable
stacks that depending on the customer
needs and I don't know where they stand
right now they seem to their business
seems to be hard mm-hm
do you think this whole web 2.0 thing
you know contribution for everybody
collaboration blah blah blah is that is
that a major driver for open source
because it has this read write web as I
think lesyk what's called it is
do you think there is a connection
between open-source and web 2.0 I think
there is and in at least two ways one of
which you just mentioned kind of mindset
of philosophy the methods and processes
that they use and of course
plain and simple technically that or
that everyone can set up a web service
in their basement just get a lamp or
lamp stack and put the software into
service the more interesting one though
is what you just pointed out the kind of
approach we actually call it we had two
men s a PV I had to I had to find a way
how to make my to work topics wiki's and
open source to fit together so I called
it open collaboration is there's an
approach to a collaboration between
people where you have no singer CEO who
can put the some on you and kind of
direct you what to do but rather as we
see for example in the case of Wikipedia
this type of collaboration is is a gala
terian meaning everyone can contribute
you're open to outside contributions you
market your project as opposed to you
hide what you're doing it's meritocratic
meaning you really value what's being
contributed based on the value and not
by who is saying it and it's
self-organizing typically open-source
processes and Wikipedia and wiki's
choose open source projects and
Wikipedia define their own process so
every project is different we do
research into open source processes it
turns out there is no single open source
process they are all different so we had
to look at more and individual practice
as well that's a different topic so if I
want to start my own business in the
context of this open source stuff
can I get VC money or I don't know you
know I mean almost VC only about really
hyped colorful end users you know well
other examples of VC money around open
source systems oh absolutely but the
good news is is the
is a lot of money around open source
companies and business models the bad
news is the train has left the platform
meaning about so examples of my SQL was
venture capital fund okay spring source
just got 10 Millions mm-hmm enterprise
DB is at like 150 million I believe and
so that's based on PostgreSQL alfresco
there lots of commercial open source
startups now I recently talked with one
venture capitalist and I thought that
story before is they themselves sat down
looked at the different markets looked
at which market in which market
open-source could be a strategic toward
a disruptive tool a tool to disrupt the
market and actively sought out
entrepreneurs to start aa open source
companies on providing gardening
supplies off for something it would that
be community open source or the other
one I think I'm pretty sure that most
look most certainly looked at commercial
open source because the profit margins
of commercial open source why are not
quite back to the good old hay days off
closed-source software us better than
the net services revenue so getting VC
money for your consulting company around
Tomcat probably won't work no I I don't
consulting companies I cannot imagine
that they get funding but my point is
they have all the VCS have already
thinly combed through the market and so
you have to have a you have to have more
than just open source and your business
model in order to get VC funding these
days you have to either unique
intellectual property or connections
distribution channels specific peoples
thing that things that could
differentiate you yeah well I guess
that's true for any VC counting anyway
so yeah I don't but the point being that
open source really just doesn't pull it
through and it's not the main thing any
longer so if that's the first thing on
your slide deck that's not a good thing
to it's like in the book market just
having work pattern on the title doesn't
maybe
a long over - unfortunately yeah well
it's may be different for better sure
yeah
things move on yeah so so we only hear
about successful open source companies
mm-hmm
I guess I think you said before that the
default case is that you go bankrupt so
are there any failed open source efforts
and I mean not you know not the
thousands of sauce holes project that
nobody cares about I mean the idea of
doing business around it and it
basically failed yeah so it's always
it's not nice to me to mention companies
that are fair but on the other hand if
it's public anyway I can only think
unfortunately at for Germans perhaps
high-profile example I don't know mine
query got their funding cut or didn't
get the next round of funding that was a
German company around collaboration
software I can't think of big time
failures right now I'm pretty sure they
are I'm just not thinking of them right
now which proves the point that you
typically only hear about the successful
thing yeah well something lame out I
mean we all remember Batman I guess and
and a sock puppet for for pet food but
yeah okay yeah so maybe that's a Silicon
Valley Lord know that man was the grocer
so convenient who would deliver for a
cheap price to your door all the
groceries you would want to her like
three hundred million but they just
brought through that cash and that was
that and now Amazon does it now Amazon
does it very cautiously because of the
map and experience I'm sure so we're
getting towards the end of this thing
you mentioned before patterns sorry
patterns mm-hmm
how does that go together with open
source do you think this whole software
pattern i yeah I'm so in this parents
thing do you think this software patents
thing is a threat to open source it's a
threat it is a threat to commercial open
source companies
and that is because if you provide
yourself in source code form it's much
easier to see whether you're infringing
on someone else's patterns so that is a
good reason why companies may not
necessarily want to open-source and
particularly if they think they actually
infringing but it's not be noticed yet
yeah I mean I don't want to go down the
whole rat hole of software pattern there
obviously we are not in the industry is
not in a good shape and they're way too
many really bad software patterns yeah
in the end I don't think though that it
will stop open-source really so patents
and open source it's a problem if you're
infringing because open source makes it
more explicit patents can be used as a
tool when you open source because as you
provide source code and with a license
that maybe doesn't cover all the bases
you can have intellectual property in
your source code that most notably than
patterns
you don't actually provision for in your
license so theoretically you could screw
your community and could go back to
companies who are using your software
and point out that they are actually
using the software for free but maybe
they want to use the commercial license
because or lo and behold they're
infringing on some of your patterns by
using that song there are the things
that I don't think it really works that
way because you do not want to annoy
your customers well there's some cases
for other intellectual property like
trademarks have been used so I believe I
hear the story in different forms from
different people from the Debian folks I
hear that the Mozilla Foundation just
didn't want them to use Firefox and
Thunderbird so it's got different names
and a Debian distribution gets
recompiled you could be compiled and has
different names you know at the Mozilla
Foundation I forgot they they told me a
different story
so that was perhaps just a coincidence
theoretically you can use trademarks to
keep keep your software users in check
but I don't think any of the
really works well I mean that's just
annoying a customer's yeah yeah after
all they're free to use their stuff our
your stuff I mean they don't have to
yeah well I mean the point is if you
come afterwards the point is they're
losing you can lock in companies who's
open source okay so anything else I
forgot to ask anything else you want to
our pearls of wisdom you want to leave
our listeners with how also wisdom or
something F whatever well in terms of
open source I mentioned this rather
amazing result you got around the total
growth the exponential growth you can
actually read up on the paper we wrote
on that topic my website will put it in
the show notes I guess excellent thank
you
the website is dubbed up top marilla dog
are e hele
org we did some investigation around a
dryer method practices and open source
because s AP wanted to know what skills
its developers need to have in order to
be effective contributors to a higher
source and because you can't go out
there and buy training for open source
because again every process is different
and there aren't actually I don't know
of any service so what are those skills
as I guess connotation is probably so
since you since you mentioned it the
headline is being able to communicate
with others and and being just a good
team player yes
so definitely social skills figure at
the top of things because it's also
distributed develop much more
distributed than before writing skills
Rob written skills are important because
a good open source project that attracts
volunteers and what-have-you
in some form documents it's process
documents all the game design decisions
some common practices someone asked a
question and back comes the link to some
summary email on the developer or
whatever mailing list which shattered
the issue two years ago it is
interesting to reflect on the changes
that open source means for developers
and developer careers
so there literally is a form of a new
form of career independent of your
employer very simple forms you can
proceed through the stages of being a
user of some open source or becoming a
developer and say you provide your first
bug fix to becoming a committer meaning
you have X you have right-right rights
to the code repository in larger
projects developers do not have
automatic write rights but rather
whatever they quote they write gets
submitted to the blue hatch or to some
mailing list and it's picked up by a
committer
and only the committer actually checks
it in it so committers are powerful
positions in open source projects and
they actually give you some independence
of your employer because it's valued by
other employers right that you are a
committer and open source projects most
notably for the professional service
firms you brush and write that can get
you another job easier also what we
observe is that by working in open
source projects you publicly document
your competence so if you are
contributing something and it gets
accepted into the codebase then you can
just point to the check in or the commit
and or in some other form show a
potential employer here I've contributed
to this project it was deemed good
quality and was accepted I interview a
lot for jobs that we have at sa P so
whenever someone tells me he's a writing
open source code I ask him send me some
salad be some fun show me the code
very good exactly that's it yeah it's
Erich gamma calls it like getting your
stripes on the uniform yeah right yeah
this is actually another way of
professional open source for the
individual developer it makes life
definitely more interesting for for
software developers ok so I guess we're
at the end mm-hmm thank you very much
for your time and I appreciate this is
cotton although it's not necessarily a
typical topic for se radio so thank you
very much
well thank you for having me this was a
lot of fun and I'm sure this is a topic
where we have can have more discussions
for another time
all right thank you thanks hello he
isn't bad mr. honker can advice from the
novels of Susan Sophists understand long
J to you and good claret excellent Java
a foul
I've coached retainer brings 200 foot
biases to mother specify software to
evict Robert it in his own so yeah a lot
of Schrager furgoneta
as if it sank that also are working a
consuming Jacques Vallee fit Seattle
order the rotation fashions in the -
seizures unexpected is amid primal after
yoga so we're in technician bhai he off
react management and zona to Lee
Williams far as the totally cool India
did he buy me a burden
- bad necessarily say socially
distracting harm there's only Elijah the
vixen manager valium Infiniti our team X
is the X pattern between as you have a
discrete direct mid Tim Hawkins I'm
trapped as it's then is not to be for
his own country does is about
en Casa for Thai BIOS ooh anime and Nam
have tycoon latencies am and who know me
Amada sister Fiona bits are traded here
informants Vanessa hunts to become
resigned and Noah cooling the colleague
ins and his arm
join a team often competent very dorm
team to avoid violence again from the
autumn heights of UN given design so
lesson on and resides about at verse
which tandem Bismil de fátima never with
playing on here I'm been weakened
lyricism missmizon business bizarre the
best mission in croissant vanilla
t-inverse could con above our hands are
tied emotion Lloyd Garrison's lawyers
are an answer cooking god of the fighter
and because no a team talking all for
Canada far vomit at so his often demands
I'm also could be enough we
from our line into vvv was apparently in
the double put a shower in singing under
Christian vice the doubles thanks for
listening to software engineering radio
if you want more information about the
podcast and all the other episodes visit
our website at se - radio dotnet if you
want to support us you can donate to the
SU radio team by on the website or you
can advertise for se radio for example
by clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
and slash dog buttons to contact the
team place an email to team and SI radio
net or if it's specific to an episode
please use the comments facility on the
website so other people can read and
react to your comments this episode of
software engineering radio as well as
all other episodes are licensed under
Creative Commons license please see the
website for details thanks to Charlie
crowd and the pot safe music Network for
the music used in this show the song is
called Vegas hard rock shuffle
[Music]